Guide to the Pleiades Club Collection 1893-1943 MSS.035
Fales Library and Special Collections
Pleiades Club Collection
1893-1943
Fales Library and Special Collections
Neiman, Howard S.
Mann, Sivia Brenner
MSS.035
4.5 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
The Pleiades Club was a Greenwich Village literary society of the early 20th century. Howard Neiman was a member of the Board of Governors throughout the Club's history, and served in other posts at the Club. The collection includes Neiman's club correspondence and printed items which illuminate aspects of the literary and artistic life of the Village of that time.
Provenance
The collection consists of papers and books of Howard S. Neiman donated to Fales Library by Sivia Brenner Mann in 1994.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Historical/Biographical Note:
The Pleiades Club emerged in 1896 from the gatherings of some members of the Greenwich Village artistic community in the small Italian restaurant of Maria del Prato on MacDougal Street. Among the customers of Maria's, the Pleiades Club named: Amos Cummings, Colonel William Gulder, Ripley Oswood Anthony, Paul Du Chaillu, Clara Louise Kellogg, Mark Twain, Valerian Gribayedoff, Signor Tagliapietra, "Billy" (W. E. S) Fales, Cleveland Moffett, Stephen Crane, "Billy" Welsh, Henry Tyrrell, Sam Chamberlain, Colonel Patton, William Garrison, George Luks, and Ernest Jarrold as its progenitors. For several seasons (each season lasted December through May) the Club continued to meet weekly at Maria's, first on Saturday and then on Sunday nights. As it became more widely known, the Club moved in search of larger quarters, first to the Black Cat (Uptown) and then to the Hungaria. After the first few years of uncertain and varying policies, in 1901 a new Board of Governors was elected, the name Pleiades Club regularly adopted, and the incorporation papers granted on January 9, 1902. After several seasons of moves, the Club settled in 1906 at the Hotel Brevoort, where it remained for most of its existence, with the exception of a few short-term stays at Reisenweber's and Hotel Martinique.
The Club's activities primarily consisted of weekly dinners, accompanied by an entertainment program, such as music performances and poetry readings, where club members and guests of honor gathered "to enjoy and foster the allied arts of Music, Drama, Art and Literature, and to Promote the spirit of good fellowship" (The Pleiad, 1931-32). The Club saw its mission as providing a friendly and appreciative audience to the inexperienced artists, helping the needy artists with free scholarships in the various branches of arts. The Club also published a yearbook, The Pleiad.
The Club apparently continued to function at least through the 1935/1936 season, since the 1936 yearbook was published (it is a part of The New York Historical Society collection).
Howard Seiger Neiman (1868-1947) was a patent attorney, editor and publisher of Textile Colorist magazine (1918-1944). Born in Norristown, PA, he received a B. S. degree from Lehigh University in 1888 and entered the dyestuff and chemical industries. Neiman had studied at New York Law School, set up offices as a patent and trademark attorney, and became a leading legal adviser for the cosmetic industry. He served as chemical expert for Leopold Cassella & Co., H. A. Metz & Co. and other concerns.
Throughout his life, Howard Neiman belonged to numerous clubs and associations. He was a member of the American Chemical Society since 1893. A charter member of the American Institute of Chemists, he was named its honorary secretary in 1946, after having served as its secretary for twenty years. He was a member of the Salesman's Association of the Synthetic Organic Chemical Manufacturers Association, the Chemists Club, Theta Delta Chi, Old Colony and the Manhasset Bay Yacht Club. He also was president of the Municipal Opera Association and a Mason Knight Templar and Shriner.
The Pleiades club was one of Neiman's long-time commitments. He was a member of the Board of Governors throughout the Club's history, served as its Secretary in 1905-1908 and again in 1928-1933, and was elected President of the Club three times.
Sources:
The Pleiad
The New York Times Obituary (Nov. 2, 1947, 73:2)
Scope and Content Note
Howard S. Neiman's collection consists of books, yearbooks, scrapbooks, letters and miscellaneous items. The material primarily relates to the Pleiades Club of the Greenwich Village, but also include some items relating to other activities of Howard Neiman.
SERIES DESCRIPTION
Series I, Books, (1899-1949): consists of books from Neiman's library, written mostly by the members of the Pleiades Club. Nearly all books and pamphlets are inscribed to Neiman by their authors. Two books have manuscript poems and correspondence laid in.
Series II, Yearbooks, (1906-1932): contains volumes of The Pleiad for years 1907-1922 (missing volumes for 1908/09, 1911/12, and 1920/21 seasons), volumes for 1927/28, 1928/29 and 1931/32 seasons and a folder containing loose pages from various issues of the yearbook (1906-1915). Six volumes are inscribed or signed by the contributors.
Series III, Correspondence, (1903-1918): comprised of over 150 letters (virtually all autograph), from minor writers, journalists, celebrities of the day, politicians, editors etc. Letters are addressed predominantly to Neiman as a secretary of the Pleiades Club, and sometimes to other Club officials (John Ryan, Edward Foley). Among the more famous names are Louis Rhead (3 letters), Secretary of State John Hay, Arthur Guiterman, Dan Beard, Otis Skinner. Several letters and postcards concerning Neiman do not relate to the Pleiades Club.
Series IV: Miscellaneous, (1893-1960): consists of two subseries
Subseries A consists of the materials relating to the Pleiades Club, such as scrapbooks and folders.
Subseries B consists of materials relating to other interests of Howard Neiman, such bound volumes of newspaper clippings and poetry, Textile Colorist editorials, selection of materials on actor George Clarke, opera libretto etc.
Arrangement
Folders are generally arranged alphabetically by subject/author heading.
The files are grouped into four series.
Missing Title
Series I: Books is arranged alphabetically by author's last name.
Series II: Yearbooks are arranged chronologically.
Series III: Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondents' last name.
Series IV: Ephemera is arranged into two subseries.
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
New York (N.Y.).; Correspondence.; Scrapbooks.; Postcards.; Clippings (information artifacts); New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; New York (N.Y.) -- Intellectual life; English literature |x Societies, etc.; Arliss, George, 1868-1946; Skinner, Otis, 1858-1942; Beard, Daniel Carter, 1850-1941; Pleiades Club; Neiman, Howard S.; Rhead, Louis, 1857-1926; Pollock, Channing, 1880-1946; Guiterman, Arthur, 1871-1943; Clarke, George, 1840-1906; Hay, John, 1838-1905; Mann, Sivia Brenner
- Series I: Books
  Scope and Content
  This series consists of books from Neiman's library, written mostly by the members of the Pleiades Club. Nearly all books and pamphlets are inscribed to Neiman by their authors. Two books have manuscript poems and correspondence laid in.
  - Bangs, John Kendrick, Olympian Nights, New York-London: Harper and Bros. Co., 1902. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Beresford, Helen, The Phantom Knight and Other Verse, Hawthorne: Hawthorne News Printing and Publishing Co., 1925. Sighed by author. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chittenden, Larry, Bermuda Verses, New York - London: Putnam's Sons, 1909. Inscribed to Neiman by author. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cole, Carter S., Lays and Lyrics, New York, n. p. 1910. Inscribed to Neiman by author. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Edwards, Harry Stillwell, Just Sweethearts: a Christmas Love Story, Mason, Georgia: Burke Co., 1919. Inscribed to Howard and Edna Neiman from cousin Sadie. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Emerson,. Edwin Jr., Popys's Ghost, Boston, 1899. Signed by author. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Emmons, Earl, Mavericks, New York: Oswald Publishing Co., 1924. Inscribed to Neiman by author. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Eudy, Mary Cummings, Quicken the Current, New York: Harper & Bros. Co., 1949. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Euwer, Antony Henderson, Cats, New York: Club Affairs Co., 1907. Inscribed to Neiman by author. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Fairchild, Lee, The Tippler's Vow, New York: De Olde Arden Press, 1908. Inscribed to Neiman by author. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Foster, Ardeen, The Poetical Works, New York: McElroy Publishing Co., 1906. Inscribed to Neiman by author. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hazzard, John Edward, Poetry an'Rot, New York: Geo F. Rammelsburg, 1906. Inscribed to Neiman by author. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Moore, Charles Forrest, One Thing and Another: Essays, New York :William Edwin Rudge, 1924. Inscribed to Neiman by author. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Moore, Charles Forrest, Parade of the Presidents, New York :William Edwin Rudge, 1928. Inscribed to Neiman by author. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Moore, Charles Forrest, The Challenge of Life, New York :William Edwin Rudge,1924 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Nelson, Frank Carleton, Along Life's Road, Auburn: The Indiana State Forum, 1927. Inscribed to Neiman by author. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Norris, Zoe Anderson, The Color of His Soul, New York Fenno & Co., 1903. Inscribed to Neiman by author. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Palmer Spaudling, Francesca di Maria, The Voyager and Other Poems, New York, n. p. 1912 Inscribed to Neiman by author. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Samuels, Maurice, The Florentines, A Play, New York: Bentano's, 1904. Inscribed to Neiman by author. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Terry, Edward Hicks Streeter, Poems, Philadelphia: The Biddle Press, 1910. Signed by author. Enclosed: two manuscript poems by Terry. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Weeks, Clara Winslow, Story of a Chinese Plate, New York: The Trow Press, 1913. Enclosed: correspondence from Clara Winslow Week to Neiman. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - What Mrs Eddy Said to Arthur Brisbane: the Celebrated Interview of the Eminent Journalist and the Founder of Christian Science, New York: Paige, 1930. Inscribed to Neiman by Sam Roan. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Series II: Yearbooks
  This series contains volumes of The Pleiad for years 1907-1922 (missing volumes for 1908/09, 1911/12, and 1920/21 seasons), volumes for 1927/28, 1928/29 and 1931/32 seasons and a folder containing loose pages from various issues of the yearbook (1906-1915). Six volumes are inscribed or signed by the contributors.
  - The Pleiad, yearbook, season 1907/08. Inscribed or signed by the contributors., 1907-1908 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Pleiad, yearbook, season 1909/10. Inscribed or signed by the contributors., 1909-1910 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - The Pleiad, yearbook, season 1910/11, 1910-1911 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - The Pleiad, yearbook, season 1912/13. Inscribed or signed by the contributors., 1912-1913 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - The Pleiad, yearbook, season 1913/14, 1913-1914 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The Pleiad, yearbook, season 1914/15, 1914-1915 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The Pleiad, yearbook, season 1915/16. Inscribed or signed by the contributors., 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - The Pleiad, yearbook, season 1916/17, 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The Pleiad, yearbook, season 1917/18. Inscribed or signed by the contributors., 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Pleiad, yearbook, season 1918/19, 1918-1919 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The Pleiad, yearbook, season 1919/20. Inscribed or signed by the contributors., 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - The Pleiad, yearbook, season 1921/22, 1921-1922 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The Pleiad, yearbook, season 1927/28, 1927-1928 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - The Pleiad, yearbook, season 1928/29, 1928-1929 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - The Pleiad, yearbook, season 1931/32, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Loose pages from various issues of the yearbook (1906-1915). (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Series III: Correspondence
  This series is comprised of over 150 letters (virtually all autograph), from minor writers, journalists, celebrities of the day, politicians, editors etc. Letters are addressed predominantly to Neiman as a secretary of the Pleiades Club, and sometimes to other Club officials (John Ryan, Edward Foley). Among the more famous names are Louis Rhead (3 letters), Secretary of State John Hay, Arthur Guiterman, Dan Beard, Otis Skinner. Several letters and postcards concerning Neiman do not relate to the Pleiades Club.
  - Incoming Letters (1903-1918), arranged alphabetically by correspondent (A-K). Correspondents: Charles A. Adams, Birdsill Andrews, A. Antone and R. Rimon, Paulette Antoine, George Arliss, John Aushire, A. Bainbridge, M. J. Baxter, Dan Beard, George Beban, Alan Bell, Helen Berensford, K. Blienniz, Gertrude Boor-Stearne, A. Brisbane, Alanson T. Briggs, Edmund Breese, Richard Carter, J. B. Coghlan, Homer Davenport, D. Delchanty, Mennes Graham Destamps, Thomas Darlington, Edith Dethson, Minnie Dupree, Paul Dufault, Alec deEbray, Lee Fairchild, Thomas Fogart Evelyn Dutton Fogg, Ardeen Foster, Spencer Frisk, Paolo S. Galazzi, Gilberte, Ch. Gilibert, Jeanne Gomelli, Frederick Grant, Ms. Greenleaf, Arthur Guiterman, Archie Gunn, James Clarence Harvey, John Hay, Hartford S. Hadley, Job E Hedges, S. F. Hershil, Shafter Howard, Franz Kaltenborn, M. Ketten, Helen Koelling, Koike (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Incoming Letters (1903-1918), arranged alphabetically by correspondent (L-Z). Harry Leighton, Sheldon Lewis, Frank Lincoln, de Lipman, Charles Battell Loomis, Wright Lorrimer, R. B. Mantell, F. C. Mathenson, Raybaudy-Massiglia, Edyth Totten McGrath, Roy L. McCardell, Burn McIntosh, Nelson Miles, J. W. Miller James Grant Milson, Esther Wall Mumford, Jan Munkacsy, E. Nagasaki, M. Nagasi, Marci Narelle, Mesrop Newton, Zoe Anderson Norris, [...] O'Carrole, R. F. Outeault, Francesca di Maria Palmer, F. Joubert Pienaar, J. C. Platt, Channing Pollock, F. K. Pulsifer, Louis Rhead, Charles. H. Roe, Caro Roma, Charles Rotland, Mrs McGarick-Russell, Charles Sarka, Theodocia Sarrisen, Maurice Samuels Julius L. Schendel, Percy Sanderson, James N Sing, Otis Skinner, Edith Sothern, N[...] Taliofarro, C. Bryson Taylor, David Warfield, Clifford Walker, Percy Winter, Bartow S. Weeks, Ethel Jackson Zimmerman. (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Series IV: Ephemera
  This series is divided into two subseries: subseries A consists of the materials relating to the Pleiades Club, such as scrapbooks and folders. Subseries B includes materials relating to other interests of Howard Neiman, such bound volumes of newspaper clippings and poetry, Textile Colorist editorials, selection of materials on actor George Clarke, opera libretto etc.
  - Subseries A: The Pleiades Club
    - Pleiades Scrapbook, season 1930-1931, contains autographs, poems and drawings by members and guests of the Club. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Club Yearbook Cloth Ex Libris Folders for year XIII, season 1906/07, 1906-1907 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      2 copies.
  - Subseries B: Howard Neiman
    - "Smoke Rings From Editor's Pipe," Howard Neiman ed., Textile Colorist, Inc., 1942. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Editorials of Textile Colorist ,1935-1943, inscribed by Neiman to his wife Edna. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Poetry Album 1897 - 1908 (?) contains printed and handwritten poems by Neiman. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1891-1895, a bound volume. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "Erinnerungslatter" undated loose leaf collection of art photographs and articles about art exhibitions. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Material relating to actor George Clarke (1893-1894) consists of four autographed letters by George Clarke, addressed to Mr. Popelon, a magazine article and 3 photographs. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Contes D'Hoffmann. Opera libretto., undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Jack Hazzard, Thinking of Yeh Christmas Time. 1914, booklet. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Letter to Neiman from Secretary of State Christian A. Herter, 23 September 1960 (Box 3, Folder 10)